Today I stand before you as a man who lives life to the full
أقف أمامكم اليوم كرجل يعيش حياته على أكمل وجه
in the here and now.
لحظة بلحظة.
But for a long time,
لكن لوقت طويل،
I lived for death.
كنت أعيش من أجل الموت.
I was a young man who believed
كنت شابًا يؤمن
that jihad is to be understood in the language of force and violence.
أن الجهاد يُفهم في لغة القوة والعنف.
I tried to right wrongs through power and aggression.
كنت أحاول أن أصحح الأخطاء عن طريق القوة والهجوم.
I had deep concerns for the suffering of others
كنت أحمل همًا كبيرًا لمعاناة الآخرين
and a strong desire to help and bring relief to them.
ورغبة قوية في أن أساعدهم وأشعرهم بالارتياح.
I thought violent jihad was noble,
كنت أفكر أن الجهاد المعنف كان نبيلًا،
chivalrous
مقدامًا،
and the best way to help.
وأنه الطريقة المثلى لتقديم المساعدة.
At a time when so many of our people --
في وقت حيث أن الكثير من الناس --
young people especially --
وخصوصًا الشباب --
are at risk of radicalization
معرضون لخطر التطرف
through groups like al-Qaeda,
على يد مجموعات مثل القاعدة،
Islamic State and others,
الدولة الإسلامية والآخرين،
when these groups are claiming
حين تدّعي هذه الجماعات
that their horrific brutality and violence are true jihad,
أن أعمالها الرهيبة والعنيفة هي الجهاد الحقيقي،
I want to say that their idea of jihad is wrong --
فإنني أريد أن أقول أن فكرتهم عن الجهاد خاطئة --
completely wrong --
خاطئة جملة وتفصيلًا --
as was mine, then.
كما كانت أفكاري، حينها.
Jihad means to strive to one's utmost.
الجهاد يعني السعي بأقصى ما لديك.
It includes exertion and spirituality,
بما في ذلك بذل الجهد والروحانية،
self-purification
تطهير النفس،
and devotion.
والإخلاص.
It refers to positive transformation
وهو يحيل إلى التحول الإيجابي
through learning, wisdom and remembrance of God.
من خلال التعلم والحكمة وذكر الله.
The word jihad stands for all those meanings as a whole.
تحمل كلمة الجهاد كل تلك المعاني.
Jihad may at times take the form of fighting,
يمكن للجهاد أحيانًا أن يأخذ شكل صراع،
but only sometimes,
لكن هذا يحدث أحيانًا فقط،
under strict conditions,
في ظروف محددة جدًا،
within rules and limits.
في نطاق حدود وقواعد معينة.
In Islam,
في الإسلام،
the benefit of an act must outweigh the harm or hardship it entails.
يجب أن تغلب المصلحة في عمل ما الضرر أو الصعوبة التي تترتب عنه.
More importantly,
وبشكل أهم،
the verses in the Koran that are connected to jihad or fighting
آيات القرآن الكريم المرتبطة بالجهاد والقتال
do not cancel out the verses that talk about forgiveness,
لا تلغي الآيات التي تتحدث عن التسامح،
benevolence
عمل الخير،
or patience.
أو الصبر.
But now I believe that there are no circumstances on earth
في اعتقادي الآن أنه لا توجد أي ظروف على كوكب الأرض
where violent jihad is permissible,
تجعل الجهاد العنيف مسموحًا به،
because it will lead to greater harm.
لأنه سيؤدي إلى أذى أكبر.
But now the idea of jihad has been hijacked.
لكن الآن، تم اختطاف فكرة الجهاد.
It has been perverted to mean violent struggle
وتم تحويلها لتعني الصراع العنيف
wherever Muslims are undergoing difficulties,
حيثما مرّ المسلمون بأوضاع صعبة،
and turned into terrorism
ووجِّهوا نحو الإرهاب
by fascistic Islamists like al-Qaeda,
بواسطة إسلاميين فاشيين مثل القاعدة،
Islamic State and others.
والدولة الإسلامية وغيرها.
But I have come to understand
لكنني توصلت لفهم
that true jihad means striving to the utmost
أن الجهاد الحقيقي هو بذل قصارى الجهد
to strengthen and live those qualities which God loves:
لتقوية وإحياء تلك الصفات التي يحبها الله:
honesty, trustworthiness,
النزاهة، الأمانة،
compassion, benevolence,
الرحمة، فعل الخير،
reliability, respect,
المصداقية، الاحترام،
truthfulness --
وقول الحق --
human values that so many of us share.
وهي قيم إنسانية يتقاسمها العديد منا.
I was born in Bangladesh,
ولدت في بنغلاديش،
but grew up mostly in England.
لكنني كبرت في بريطانيا.
And I went to school here.
وذهبت للمدرسة هناك.
My father was an academic,
كان والدي أكاديميًا،
and we were in the UK through his work.
وقد جئنا لبريطانيا من خلال عمله.
In 1971 we were in Bangladesh when everything changed.
سنة 1971، كنا في بنغلاديش حين تغير كل شيء.
The War of Independence impacted upon us terribly,
أثّرت علينا حرب الاستقلال بشكل فظيع،
pitting family against family,
لتضع الأسر في مواجهة بعضها البعض،
neighbor against neighbor.
والجيران في مواجهة بعضهم البعض.
And at the age of 12 I experienced war,
عشت أجواء الحرب في سن 12 سنة،
destitution in my family,
الفقر المدقع مع عائلتي،
the deaths of 22 of my relatives in horrible ways,
ووفاة 22 من أقاربي بطرق بشعة،
as well as the murder of my elder brother.
وكذلك مقتل أخي الأكبر.
I witnessed killing ...
شهدت على القتل...
animals feeding on corpses in the streets,
رأيت حيوانات تقتتات على الجثث في الشوارع،
starvation all around me,
الجوع يحوم حولي،
wanton, horrific violence --
عنف وحشي فظيع --
senseless violence.
عنف لا معنى له.
I was a young man,
كنت شابًا،
teenager, fascinated by ideas.
مراهقًا، مفتونًا بالأفكار.
I wanted to learn,
كنت أريد أن أتعلم،
but I could not go to school for four years.
لكنني لم أستطع أن أذهب إلى المدرسة لأربع سنوات.
After the War of Independence,
وبعد حرب الاستقلال،
my father was put in prison for two and a half years,
سُجن أبي لمدة عامين ونصف،
and I used to visit him every week in prison,
كنت أزوره كل أسبوع في السجن،
and homeschooled myself.
وكنت أدرِّس نفسي في البيت.
My father was released in 1973
أطلق سراح أبي سنة 1973
and he fled to England as a refugee,
فغادر نحو بريطانيا كلاجئ،
and we soon followed him.
والتحقنا به بعد وقت قصير.
I was 17.
كنت حينها في الـ 17 من عمري.
So these experiences gave me
إذًا فهذه التجارب أعطتني
a sharp awareness of the atrocities and injustices in the world.
إدراكًا عميقًا للأعمال الوحشية والظلم في العالم.
And I had a strong desire --
كانت لدي رغبة قوية --
a very keen, deep desire --
رغبة عميقة وأكيدة --
to right wrongs
على تصحيح الأخطاء
and help the victims of oppression.
ومساعدة ضحايا الظلم.
While studying at college in the UK,
عندما كنت أدرس في الجامعة في بريطانيا،
I met others who showed me how I could channel that desire
التقيت أشخاصًا آخرين أروني كيفية توجيه تلك الرغبة
and help through my religion.
والمساعدة من خلال ديني.
And I was radicalized --
فأصبحت متطرفًا --
enough to consider violence correct,
متطرفًا بما يكفي لأعتبر أن العنف أمر صحيح،
even a virtue under certain circumstances.
بل وحتى اعتباره أمرًا محمودًا في ظروف معينة.
So I became involved in the jihad in Afghanistan.
لذلك انخرطت في الجهاد في أفغانستان.
I wanted to protect the Muslim Afghan population against the Soviet army.
كنت أريد أن أحمي المسلمين الأفغان من الجيش السوفياتي.
And I thought that was jihad:
فظننت أن ذلك هو الجهاد:
my sacred duty,
واجبي المقدس،
which would be rewarded by God.
والذي سيجازيني عنه الله.
I became a preacher.
أصبحت خطيبًا.
I was one of the pioneers of violent jihad in the UK.
كنت أحد قادة الجهاد العنيف في بريطانيا.
I recruited,
قمت بالحشد،
I raised funds, I trained.
جمعت الأموال، و درّبت.
I confused true jihad
خلطت بين الجهاد الحقيقي
with this perversion as presented by the fascist Islamists --
وبين هذا الانحراف كما يقدمه هؤلاء الفاشيون الإسلاميون --
these people who use the idea of jihad
هؤلاء الناس الذين استعملوا فكرة الجهاد
to justify their lust for power, authority and control on earth:
لتبرير لهفتهم على القوة والسلطة والتحكم في الأرض:
a perversion perpetuated today by fascist Islamist groups
انحراف مستمر إلى اليوم من طرف الجماعات الإسلامية الفاشية
like al-Qaeda, Islamic State and others.
مثل القاعدة، والدولة الإسلامية وغيرها.
For a period of around 15 years,
لمدة تقارب 15 سنة،
I fought for short periods of time
قاتلت لفترات قصيرة
in Kashmir and Burma,
في كشمير وبورما،
besides Afghanistan.
إلى جانب أفغانستان.
Our aim was to remove the invaders,
هدفنا كان طرد المحتلين،
to bring relief to the oppressed victims
وإغاثة الضحايا المظلومين
and of course to establish an Islamic state,
وبالطبع تأسيس دولة إسلامية،
a caliphate for God's rule.
خليفة في أرض الله.
And I did this openly.
قمت بهذا علنًا.
I didn't break any laws.
لم أنتهك أية قوانين.
I was proud and grateful to be British --
كنت فخورًا و ممتنًا أنني بريطاني --
I still am.
ولا زلت كذلك.
And I bore no hostility against this, my country,
ولم أحمل أي عداء ضد بلدي،
nor enmity towards the non-Muslim citizens,
ولا ضغينة على المواطنين غير المسلمبن،
and I still don't.
ولا زلت.
During one battle in Afghanistan,
خلال إحدى المعارك في أفغانستان،
some British men and I formed a special bond
جمعتني علاقة وطيدة أنا وبعض الرجال البريطانيين
with a 15-year-old Afghani boy,
بفتى أفغاني كان عمره 15 سنة،
Abdullah,
عبد الله،
an innocent, loving and lovable kid
طفل بريء، محبوب وودود.
who was always eager to please.
كان يسعى دائمًا لإرضائنا.
He was poor.
كان فقيرًا.
And boys like him did menial tasks in the camp.
وكان الفتيان في مثل سنه يقومون بمهام وضيعة داخل المخيم.
And he seemed happy enough,
كان يبدو سعيدًا،
but I couldn't help wonder --
لكنني ما فتئت أتساءل --
his parents must have missed him dearly.
لا بد أن والديه اشتاقا إليه جدًا.
And they must have dreamt about a better future for him.
لا بد وأنهما كانا يحلمان بمستقبل أفضل له.
A victim of circumstance caught up in a war,
ضحية ظروف حبسته في الحرب،
cruelly thrust upon him
اصطدمت به بكل قسوة
by the cruel circumstances of the time.
ظروف الزمن القاسية.
One day I picked up this unexploded mortar shell in a trench,
ذات يوم، التقطت قذيفة هاون غير منفجرة من خندق،
and I had it deposited in a makeshift mud hut lab.
ووضعتها في مختبر مؤقت مصنوع من طين.
And I went out on a short, pointless skirmish --
وذهبت إلى مناوشة قصيرة لا طائل منها --
always pointless,
هي دائمًا كذلك،
And I came back a few hours later to discover he was dead.
عدت بعدها بساعات لأجد أنه قد مات.
He had tried to recover explosives from that shell.
لقد حاول أن يستخرج مواد متفجرة من تلك القذيفة
It exploded, and he died a violent death,
فانفجرت، فمات موتة فظيعة،
blown to bits by the very same device that had proved harmless to me.
فأردي صريعًا بنفس الجهاز الذي لم يكن مؤذيا بالنسبة لي أبدًا.
So I started to question.
فبدأت أتساءل.
How did his death serve any purpose?
ما الهدف الذي خدمه موت هذا الفتى؟
Why did he die and I lived?
لماذا مات هو وبقيت أنا حيًا؟
I carried on.
استمريت.
I fought in Kashmir.
قاتلت في كشمير.
I also recruited for the Philippines,
حشدت أشخاصًا من أجل الفلبين،
Bosnia and Chechnya.
البوسنة والشيشان.
And the questions grew.
فازدادت الأسئلة.
Later in Burma,
لاحقًا في بورما،
I came across Rohingya fighters,
صادفت مقاتلي الروهينيا،
who were barely teenagers,
الذين كانوا بالكاد في سن المراهقة،
born and brought up in the jungle,
ولدوا وترعرعوا في الغابة،
carrying machine guns and grenade launchers.
وهم يحملون رشاشات وقاذفات قنابل.
I met two 13-year-olds with soft manners and gentle voices.
قابلت مراهقين في سن 13 سنة كانا مؤدبين وأصواتهما هادئة.
Looking at me,
كانا ينظران إليّ،
they begged me to take them away to England.
ويتوسلان إليّ أن آخذهما بعيدًا إلى بريطانيا.
They simply wanted to go to school --
كانا ببساطة يريدان أن يذهبا إلى المدرسة --
that was their dream.
كان هذا حلمهما.
My family --
عائلتي --
my children of the same age --
وأطفالي في نفس السن --
were living at home in the UK,
كانوا يعيشون في بريطانيا،
going to school,
يذهبون للمدرسة،
living a safe life.
ويعيشون حياة آمنة.
And I couldn't help wonder
ولكنني ما فتئت أتساءل
how much these young boys must have spoken to one another
كم تحدّث هذان الفتيان لبعضهما البعض
about their dreams for such a life.
عن أحلامهما للحصول على حياة كهذه.
Victims of circumstances:
ضحايا الظروف:
these two young boys,
هذان الفتيان،
sleeping rough on the ground, looking up at the stars,
وهما يفترشان الأرض وينظران للنجوم،
cynically exploited by their leaders
وقد تم استغلالهما بسخرية من طرف قادتهما
for their personal lust for glory and power.
من أجل نزوة شخصية نحو المجد والقوة.
I soon witnessed boys like them killing one another
بعدها بقليل شهدت فتيانًا يقتلون بعضهم البعض
in conflicts between rival groups.
في صراعات بين المجموعات المتناحرة.
And it was the same everywhere ...
وقد كان الحال كذلك في كل مكان...
Afghanistan, Kashmir, Burma,
أفغانستان، كشمير، بورما،
Philippines, Chechnya;
الفلبين، الشيشان؛
petty warlords got the young and vulnerable to kill one another
حيث يزج قادة الحروب بالشباب ليقتلوا بعضهم البعض
in the name of jihad.
باسم الجهاد.
Muslims against Muslims.
مسلمون ضد المسلمين.
Not protecting anyone against invaders or occupiers;
ليس من أجل حماية أي أحد ضد محتل أو مستعمر؛
not bringing relief to the oppressed.
وليس لرفع الظلم عن المظلومين.
Children being used,
يتم استخدام الأطفال،
cynically exploited;
واستغلالهم ببشاعة؛
people dying in conflicts
كان الناس يموتون في صراعات
which I was supporting in the name of jihad.
كنت أدعمها باسم الجهاد.
And it still carries on today.
وهي لا زالت مستمرة حتى اليوم.
Realizing that the violent jihad
مع إدراكي أن الجهاد المعنف
I had engaged in abroad
الذي انخرطت فيه في الخارج
was so different --
كان مختلفًا جدًا --
such a chasm between what I had experienced
كانت هناك هوة بين ما شهدته
and what I thought was sacred duty --
وبين ما كنت أعنقد أنه واجب مقدس --
I had to reflect on my activities here in the UK.
كان عليّ أن أعيد النظر في أنشطتي هنا في بريطانيا.
I had to consider my preaching,
كان علي أن أعيد النظر في خطبي،
recruiting, fund-raising,
في الحشد، جمع الأموال،
training,
التدريب،
but most importantly, radicalizing --
لكن بشكل أخص في التطرف --
sending young people to fight and die
وإرسال شباب للقتال والموت
as I was doing --
كما كنت أفعل --
all totally wrong.
كل ذلك كان خاطئًا جدًا.
So I got involved in violent jihad in the mid '80s,
إذًا فقد انخرطت في الجهاد العنيف أواسط الثمانينات،
starting with Afghanistan.
بدءًا من أفغانستان.
And by the time I finished it was in the year 2000.
وبحلول الوقت الذي أنهيت فيه، حلّت سنة 2000.
I was completely immersed in it.
كنت منغمسًا فيها.
All around me people supported,
كان الناس من حولي يشجعون،
applauded,
ويصفقون،
even celebrated what we were doing in their name.
ويحتفلون حتى بما كنت أقوم به باسمهم.
But by the time I learned to get out,
بحلول الوقت الذي تعلمت فيه أن أخرج،
completely disillusioned in the year 2000,
كانت خيبة أملي الكبيرة سنة 2000،
15 years had passed.
15 سنة مرت.
So what goes wrong?
ما الخطب؟
We were so busy talking about virtue,
كنا مشغولين بالحديث عن الفضيلة،
and we were blinded by a cause.
لكننا كنا معميين بالقضية.
And we did not give ourselves a chance to develop a virtuous character.
ولم نعط لأنفسنا الفرصة لنطور سلوكًا حسنًا.
We told ourselves we were fighting for the oppressed,
كنا نقول لأنفسنا أننا كنا نقاتل من أجل المظلومين،
but these were unwinnable wars.
لكن تلك كانت حروبًا خاسرة.
We became the very instrument through which more deaths occurred,
لقد أصبحنا الأدوات ذاتها التي تُحصد بها المزيد من الأرواح،
complicit in causing further misery
والتي تشارك في وقوع مآسي أكبر
for the selfish benefit of the cruel few.
من أجل مصالح أنانية للقلة الجشعة.
So over time,
مع مرور الزمن،
a very long time,
زمن طويل،
I opened my eyes.
فتحت عينيّ.
I began to dare
بدأت أجرؤ
to face the truth,
على مواجهة الحقيقة،
to think,
وعلى التفكير،
to face the hard questions.
ومواجهة الأسئلة الصعبة.
I got in touch with my soul.
بدأت ألمس روحي.
What have I learned?
ما الذي تعلمته؟
That people who engage in violent jihadism,
أن الناس الذين ينخرطون في الجهاد المسلح،
that people who are drawn to these types of extremisms,
أن الناس الذين تم جرّهم لهذه الأنواع من التطرف
are not that different to everyone else.
ليسوا مختلفين عن البقية.
But I believe such people can change.
لكنني أؤمن أنه يمكن لهؤلاء الناس أن يتغيروا.
They can regain their hearts and restore them
يمكن أن يستعيدوا قلوبهم وأن يصلحوها
by filling them with human values that heal.
بأن يملؤوها بالقيم الإنسانية الشافية.
When we ignore the realities,
حينما نتجاهل الوقائع،
we discover that we accept what we are told without critical reflection.
نكتشف أننا نتقبل ما يقال لنا دون تفكير نقدي.
And we ignore the gifts and advantages that many of us would cherish
ونتجاهل النعم والمزايا التي قد يحتفي بها العديد منا
even for a single moment in their lives.
ولو للحظة واحدة في حياتهم.
I engaged in actions I thought were correct.
انخرطتُ في أعمال كنت أظنها صحيحة.
But now I began to question how I knew what I knew.
لكنني الآن بدأت أتساءل كيف عرفت ما عرفته.
I endlessly told others to accept the truth,
دائمًا ما كنت أقول للآخرين أن يتقبّلوا الحقيقة،
but I failed to give doubt its rightful place.
لكنني فشلت في أن أعطي للشك مكانه الصحيح.
This conviction that people can change is rooted in my experience,
قناعتي هذه بأنه يمكن للناس أن يتغيروا آتية من خبرتي الشخصية،
my own journey.
من رحلتي الخاصة.
Through wide reading,
من خلال قراءات عديدة،
reflecting,
وتفكير،
contemplation, self-knowledge,
وتأمل ومعرفة للنفس،
I discovered,
اكتشفت،
I realized that Islamists' world of us and them is false and unjust.
أدركت أن عالم الإسلاميين "نحن وهُم" مزيف وغيرعادل.
Through considering the uncertainties in all that we had asserted,
مع اعتبار كل ما شهدناه،
to the inviolable truths,
الحقائق التي لا مفر منها،
incontestable truths,
والحقائق التي لا تقبل الجدال،
I developed a more nuanced understanding.
كوّنت فهمًا أكثر دقة.
I realized that in a world crowded with variation and contradiction,
أدركت أن العالم مكتظ بأنواع الاختلافات والتناقضات،
foolish preachers,
بدعاة حمقى،
only foolish preachers like I used to be,
فقط الدعاة الحمقى كما كنت،
see no paradox in the myths and fictions they use to assert authenticity.
من لا يرون تناقضات في الأساطير والوقائع التي يستعملونها لتأكيد صحتها.
So I understood the vital importance of self-knowledge,
إذًا فأنا أعي الأهمية الحيوية لمعرفة النفس،
political awareness
للإدراك السياسي
and the necessity for a deep and wide understanding
وضرورة وجود فهم عميق وواسع
of our commitments and our actions,
لالتزاماتنا وأفعالنا،
how they affect others.
وكيفية تأثيرها على الآخرين.
So my plea today to everyone,
لذا فطلبي اليوم من الجميع،
especially those who sincerely believe in Islamist jihadism ...
خصوصًا من يؤمنون بصدق بالجهادية الإسلامية...
refuse dogmatic authority;
ارفضوا السلطة العقائدية؛
let go of anger, hatred and violence;
تخلوا عن الغضب والكراهية والعنف،
learn to right wrongs
تعلموا تصحيح الأخطاء
without even attempting to justify cruel, unjust and futile behavior.
دون اللجوء لتبرير سلوك بشع وظالم.
Instead create a few beautiful and useful things
عوضًا عن ذلك، اصنعوا بعضًا من الأشياء الجميلة والمفيدة
that outlive us.
التي تجعلنا نعمِّر طويلًا.
Approach the world, life,
تقرّبوا من العالم، من الحياة،
with love.
بحب.
Learn to develop
تعلموا كيف تطورون
or cultivate your hearts
وتزرعون قلوبكم
to see goodness, beauty and truth in others and in the world.
لتروا الخير والجمال والحقيقة في الآخرين وفي العالم.
That way we do matter more to ourselves ...
وبذلك سنكون ذوي قيمة أكثر لأنفسنا...
to each other,
لبعضنا البعض،
to our communities
لمجتمعاتنا
and, for me, to God.
وبالنسبة لي، لله.
This is jihad --
هذا هو الجهاد --
my true jihad.
جهادي الحقيقي.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)